hello and welcome to the fourth tutorial
on how to program in gript 2 in this
tutorial I'm going to teach you a bit
about you know actual programming now so
let's open level editor and here's our
little level let's drag a level NPC in
NPCs aren't
just characters like people they can
also be lights or doors and things like
that and they only run when the player
is in the level so let's double click it
and you see all this gript one junk and
we can take that out let's type client
side client side everything under client
side will run for just the player
everything above it will run for all the
players in the level I'll show you
examples later and probably in the next
tutorial but anyway let's type function
on create
now functions everything in gript is run
in ran in functions
functions do stuff okay like function
uncreated every time the player enters a
level for the very first
time everything in here will run let's
say the player enters a level it runs
then the player leaves the level and
comes back it won't run but if the
player joins the Ser like reconnects the
server then it'll run again fun let's do
function on player
enters it's similar to on created
except it's going to run every time the
player enters the
level now these parentheses are needed
for one well I'll probably go over them
later since we don't really need to
right now these brackets are what is ran
everything in the brackets is ran the
brackets can be like like this or it can
be anywhere you want but I like to put
them like this let's double space here
and
type player. chat is equal to high semic
column now as soon as the player enters
the level for the VAR SE time it'll run
this this what's in the
brackets player. chat this is the
player's chat this is the
player and this is his chat is equal to
oh
is equal to the text high if you take
out the quotes it's something completely
different but we'll go over that later
cuz you know it's made well it's just
we'll go over it later you'll know soon
probably in a later tutorial but anyway
we'll close the program save it and
upload I say hi
now now let's go back into the program
and change it to
this do Shad equals high
this is the MPC and this. chat is the
same as the player's chat so the play
the NPC is going to say hi as soon as
the player enters the level for the very
first
time oh no that I do it right no that I
save I did save
it upload there there's the NPC now it's
saying hi so anyway that's it for this
tutorial and oh no never mind I have one
more thing to show
sleep like here here's an example of
it I have these two
text things as soon as I save save it
and upload it it's going to say bye
but it said hello here it should be
saying hello then it'll say bye well
well it it does say hello but instantly
after it says hello it's going to run
this and say bye but let's say we want
to delay between them so we put sleep in
parenthesis the amount of seconds we
want semicolon oh I almost forgot semic
colum here if you don't put a semic
colum it's not going to
work
so we'll put
sleep three that will wait 3 seconds now
we
save
upload it says hello Waits 3 seconds
says bye and again if we take this out
for example we can just take it out like
this by adding two slashes that'll make
this a comment and it will not affect
the program we
close and upload it'll just say bye it
won't say hello because there's no delay
between them anyway that's it for this
tutorial I'll see you in the next
tutorial uh so bye